Guide to the United States Adjutant General's records: 41st Infantry Division 1940-1945
Montana Historical Society
United States Adjutant General's Office records: 41st Infantry Division 222
1940-1945
Montana Historical Society Archives
MF 507
United States. Adjutant-General's Office
33 reels of film.
These records of the United States Adjutant General's Office consist of 32 reels of "Morning Reports," September 1940-August 1943, April-July and September-October 1944, and March-June 1945, listing current location of each military unit within the 41st Infantry Division, and the soldiers on active duty in that unit. Some reports also include narrative accounts on actions. A few of the reels include units in Europe, North Africa, and Alaska. There is also 1 reel of "Annexes to Operations Reports, 186th, Biak."
The United States Adjutant General is the chief administrative officer within the military, and in this context specifically the Army. When a National Guard unit becomes activated and Federalized, this is the office which will handle all of the administrative functions of the unit. The 41st Infantry Division was activated on September 16, 1940 from the National Guard Division of Idaho, Montana, Oregon, Washington, and Wyoming. It served in the Pacific theatre during the Second World War and participated in the New Guinea, Southern Philippines, and Papuan campaigns. The Division also served on occupation duty for a brief period of time but only rarely throughout the war did it operate as a complete unit. Its three infantry regiments (162nd, 163rd, and 186th) were most often detached on separate operations and in many cases took on the designation of a specified task force.
These records of the United States Adjutant General's Office consist of 32 reels of "Morning Reports," September 1940-August 1943, April-July and September-October 1944, and March-June 1945, listing current location of each military unit within the 41st Infantry Division, and the soldiers on active duty in that unit. Some reports also include narrative accounts on actions. A few of the reels include units in Europe, North Africa, and Alaska. There is also 1 reel of "Annexes to Operations Reports, 186th, Biak."
First 3 reels arranged by military unit, for period 1940-1943. The remaining reels are arranged by year and month, and then by military unit involved. Some reels filmed in poor order.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
MC 364 Hargis Westerfield Collection: 41st Infantry Division.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
United States. Army. Infantry Division, 41st.
Biak Island, Battle of, Indonesia, 1944; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--New Guinea.; World War, 1939-1945--South Pacific.
Military
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Morning reports: 161st - 162nd Infantry (United States to New Guinea), 1940 September-1943 July (Reel 1)
- Morning reports: 162nd, Hqrs - Co. I (United States to New Guinea), 1940 September-1943 July (Reel 2)
- Morning reports: 162nd, Co. K-L, Medical Detachment; 163rd all units; 164th Anti-Tank and Service Cos.(United States to New Guinea), 1940 September-1943 July (Reel 3)
- Morning reports: 148th-165th (New Guinea, Alaska), 1943 August (Reel 4)
- Morning reports: 116th Engineers-135th Medical Regiment (New Guinea), 1944 April (Reel 5)
- Morning reports: 185th (shipboard); 162nd Hqrs-Med. Det.; 324th Field Artillery; 20th RCD; 8th Air Force; 14th Chemical Battalion; 20th Station Hospital (scattered locations), 1944 April (Reel 6)
- Morning reports: 143rd – 163rd (New Guinea), 1944 April (Reel 7)
- Morning reports: 163rd – 218th (New Guinea), 1944 April (Reel 8)
- Morning reports: 158th – 163rd, 412th - 469th (New Guinea), 1944 May (Reel 9)
- Morning reports: 287th - 411th; 163rd – 165th (New Guinea), 1944 May (Reel 10)
- Morning reports: 622nd, 222nd – 276th, 186th – 208th (New Guinea), 1944 June (Reel 11)
- Morning reports: 34th MRU – 63rd (New Guinea), June 1944 (Reel 12)
- Morning reports: 108th – 126th (New Guinea), 1944 June (Reel 13)
- Morning reports: 155th – 185th (New Guinea), 1944 June (Reel 14)
- Morning reports: 186th – 227th (Biak and Aitape, New Guinea), 1944 June (Reel 15)
- Morning reports: 55th; 429th Signal Cons.- 850th (scattered locations including Algiers and Devon, England); 163rd (Biak, New Guinea); 2677th (Italy); scattered units, 1944 June (Reel 16)
- Morning reports: 34th-53rd (New Guinea), 1944 July (Reel 17)
- Morning reports: 162nd-167th (New Guinea), 1944 July (Reel 18)
- Morning reports: 181st 186th (Aitape, New Guinea); 932nd and 437th (Italy); 222nd – 265th (New Guinea); 186th – 185th (Biak and New Britain, New Guinea); 1301st (Tidworth Park, England), 1944 July (Reel 19)
- Morning reports: 161st (Aitape, New Guinea); 162nd (Biak, New Guinea); 136th (New Guinea), 1944 September (Reel 20)
- Morning reports: 88th Signal- 108th (Philippines), 1945 March (Reel 21)
- Morning reports: 114th – 115th; 246th; 108th; 163rd; 503rd; 168th; 205th -222nd (Philippines), 1945 March (Reel 22)
- Morning reports: 155th - 164th (Philippines), 1945 March (Reel 23)
- Morning reports: 167th - 186th (Philippines), 1945 March (Reel 24)
- Morning reports: 196th - 204th; 314th; 5235th; 116th -170th (Philippines); scattered units in Belgium and France [parts of film barely legible], 1945 March (Reel 25)
- Morning reports: 3326th Service; 775th Tank; 849th Ordinance; 893rd - 895th Medical Clearing; 947th Field Artillery; 1011th Engineers; 1129 Engineers; 1136th Construction; 1164th Engineers; 1623rd Engineers; 3326th Service; 1279th Engineers; 1458th Engineer Boat Maintenance; 1541st Engineers; 1679th Engineers; 1762nd; 3295th Signal; 3327th Service; 3498th Ordinance; 162nd (Zamboanga, Philippines); 160th, 1945 April (Reel 26)
- Morning reports: 161st Parachute Engineers; 163rd Ordinance; 156th - 163rd; 462nd parachute; 411th Medical; 596th Field Artillery; 531st; 343rd; 533rd-543rd Engineers Boat SR; 593rd-595th Field Artillery; 603rd Medical (Philippines), 1945 April (Reel 27)
- Morning reports: 263rd Medical; 272nd Service; 288th Signal; 304th Signal; 306th Engineers and Medical; 154th Engineers; 143rd; 146th; 185th – 213th (Philippines), 1945 April (Reel 28)
- Morning reports: 162nd - 163rd (Philippines), 1945 May (Reel 29)
- Morning reports: 185th - 246th (Philippines), 1945 May (Reel 30)
- Morning reports: 117th – 167th (Philippines), 1945 June (Reel 31)
- Morning reports: 182nd; 163rd; 143rd; 4438th Quartermaster; 190th - 221st (Philippines), 1945 June (Reel 32)
- Annexes to Operations Reports, 186th, (Biak), undated (Reel 33)